Finding Aid for Billie Louise Edwards Papers, 1981-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Billie Louise Edwards Papers, 1981-1993 1987-1992
Edwards, Billie Louise, 1947-1995.
1.5 linear feet
0591 Aa 2
Billie Louise Edwards was a feminist, activist, lesbian, motorcyclist, co-parent, Metropolitan Community Church preacher, and clinical psychologist; she was also co-director of the University of Michigan Lesbian-Gay Male Programs Office (LGMPO) from 1987 to 1993. The Edwards papers include her educational materials and writings, training materials and correspondence from the LGMPO, audio cassettes from her ministry, and a photographic portrait.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Ayron Smith-Douglas (donor no. 9613 ) on June 27, 2005.
The collection is open to research.
Billie Edwards was born in 1947 to a military family and moved frequently in her youth. She joined the Marine Corps in 1966 and received training in photography. She was dishonorably discharged in 1967 for her sexual orientation. President Carter had this changed to an Honorable Discharge in 1977. She worked several years in the graphic arts and later trained to be a draftsman. She became a minister with the Metropolitan Community Church in Oklahoma, later ministering in northern Virginia and Detroit. She received a Bachelor of Arts in Psychology from the Union for Experimenting Colleges and Universities in Los Angeles, California in 1985 and a Master of Arts in Humanistic and Clinical Psychology from the Center for Humanistic Studies in Detroit, Michigan in 1986.
Ms. Edwards was hired as the co-director of the University of Michigan Lesbian-Gay Male Programs Office (LGMPO) in 1987. During her tenure there, she established the Educational Outreach Program, provided counseling for women and organized programs for the gay, lesbian and bi-sexual community. She resigned effective January 31, 1993 to protest against the university's decision to take counseling away from the office. She died at age 48 in 1995 of a brain tumor.
The Billie Edwards papers document her work as a lesbian-gay rights activist and co-director of the University of Michigan's Lesbian-Gay Male Program Office and her work as a minister in Metropolitan Community Church in Oklahoma City. The papers are organized into five series: Miscellaneous Personal Papers, Writings, Research Material, LGMPO Training, and LGMPO Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Edwards, Billie Louise, 1947-1995.; Coming out (Sexual orientation); Lesbians--Michigan.; Sexual orientation--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Lesbian-Gay Male Programs Office.; Women clergy--Michigan.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Edwards, Billie Louise, 1947-1995.; Sexual orientation.; Sermons.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Miscellaneous Personal Papers
  The Miscellaneous Personal Papers (0.3 linear feet) include biographical information, photographs, some of her journals and schoolwork, and five audio cassettes of sermons and a workshop. Newspaper articles of interviews are included with the biographic materials. Several journals are included in spiral bound notebooks.
  - Biographical Records and Photographs (Box 1)
  - Educational and Ministry Records (Box 1)
  - Quitting the LGMPO, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Audio-cassettes
    - Self Esteem Workshop, November 2, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Sermons
      - Oklahoma City, December 6, 1981 (Box 1)
      - Rockville MCC, November 3, 1985, 2 cassettes (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
  - Notebooks and Journals (Box 1)
  - Drafting Examples, 1984 (Box 1)
- Writings
  Edwards' Writings (0.2 linear feet) include her thesis as well as other educational papers and articles written while at the LGMPO about multi-culturalism.
  - "A framework for the study of pathological symbiosis in dysfunctional Lesbian couples" ca. 1985 (Box 1)
  - Thesis Proposal-"A Different Drummer" and Course Paper-"Family Study", 1986 (Box 1)
  - Thesis-"A Different Drummer", 1986 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous School Papers (Box 1)
  - Multi-cultural Teaching (writings, memos), 1990-1992 (Box 1)
- Research Material
  The Research Material (0.3 linear feet) includes research on sexuality and sexual health.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Gay-Lesbian Sexual Health Material (Box 1)
- LGMPO Training
  LGMPO Training papers (0.5 linear feet) are notable for the Educational Outreach Program material along with other varied programs. These programs include workshops on Crisis Intervention and Multi-Culturalism as well as training for Hotlines, Resident Staff, and Peer Counselors. Information about Lesbian Coming-Out Support Groups are also included in this series.
  - Educational Outreach Program (Box 1)
  - Curriculum for 10-week Coming Out Support Group (Box 1)
  - Lesbian Coming-Out Support Group (Box 1)
  - Crisis Intervention Workshop (Box 2)
  - Hotline Training (Box 2)
  - Multi-Cultural Workshop (Box 2)
  - Peer Counselor Training (Box 2)
  - Resident Staff Training (Box 2)
  - Training Programs Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Workshop Forms (Box 2)
- LGMPO Miscellaneous
  The LGMPO Miscellaneous papers (0.2 linear feet) includes correspondence both within and without the organization as well as papers from specific groups such as the Design and Library groups.
  - Intra-office Correspondence and Notes, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1988-1992 (Box 2)
  - Co-Group Notes, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Design Group (Box 2)
  - Library Group Notes (Box 2)
  - Gay Pride March, 1992-1993 (Box 2)